Bob Crozier World War II military intelligence map and photograph collection
Geography & Map Division Library of Congress
Bob Crozier World War II military intelligence map and aerial photograph collection. 1943-1946
G5721.S7 coll .C7 Crozier
20 maps
15 aerial photographs
1 booklet
Geography & Map Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Bob Crozier served as a Technical Sergeant in the 654th Topographic Engineers from 1943 to 1946. Crozier was part of the American First Army under General Omar Bradley. He donated a collection of photos, photo maps and maps created during World War II to the Geography and Map Division. The collection consists of 36-page booklet that describes the process of aerial reconnaissance and mapping, 15 aerial photographs, and 20 maps. Perhaps the most unique items are a captured German map that depicts Caen and a rare commemorative map of the U.S. and Russian contact at the Elbe River in 1945.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
Organizations
Germany. Heer. Abteilung für Kriegskarten- und Vermessungswesen.; United States. Army. Army, 1st.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945--Maps.
Titles
Man who wins battles, is the man who gets there "fustest with the mostest intelligence"
Form/Genre
Maps.
Provenance
Bob Crozier donated the materials as a gift to the Division in 1993.
Access and Restrictions
The Bob Crozier World War II military intelligence map and photograph collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Geography & Map Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 36-page booklet that describes the process of aerial reconnaissance and mapping, 15 aerial photographs, and 20 maps.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into seven series
Series I Booklet
Series II Aerial Photos
Series III Photo-Maps
Series IV France Field Operational Road Maps
Series V Captured German Maps Depicting Caen and Surrouding Regions
Series VI Celebratory Maps of First United States Army in Europe
Series VII Various War Maps
Container List
- Booklet
  36-page booklet describes the duties of the pilots and the photo lab capabilities.
  - Prepared by the Reconnaissance Organization Serving the First Army 1944, 30th Photo RCN.SQ., 67th TAC.RCN.GP., France 1944 (Item 1)
- Aerial Photographs
  15 aerial photographs of France and Germany.
  Photographs used to help create maps.
  - Photograph of France Sheet 34/18. SE 1944, See: Map France 100,000 "Bayeux, St. Lo, Vire" Road Map 23. (Item 2)
  - Six Photographs of "Rhine River Bank Study" Map 1944 (Item 3-8)
    See: Map "Rhine River Study" Sheet G.
  - Four Photographs of Koblenz, Germany, 1:25,000 Sheet 5611 1944, See: Map "Koblenz" Sheet 5611. (Item 9-12)
  - Four Photographs of the Ruhr River Sheet 5611 1944 (Item 13-16)
- Photo Maps
  Crozier: "All maps were compiled from aerial photos created by the 30th photo reeonnaisanoe squadron flying P-38s Lightning. The scale depends on the height in which the sortie took place. Cameras ranged from 24 inch for mappinq to 36-40 inch for larqe scale. Shutter speads were extremely fast in their time- up to 1/800 second."
  - Cherbourg, Sheet E-24 1944, 1:25,000 (Item 17)
    "As I recall, our first combat field map printed while in England, highlighting primary and secondary roads and railroads. Note how secondary roads often dead end!"
    Gridded map
    Restricted
  - Northwestern Germany Photomap, Series Z, Sheet Q-13 1945, 1:10,000; Shows Rhine River turn at Neuwied. (Item 18)
  - Rhine River Photomap, Section X, Sheet B-5 1944, 1:9,000; Rhine River at Koeln. (Item 19)
- France Field Operational Road Maps
  Five maps showing roads and railroads in Normandy and adjacent areas.
  Towns and cities indicate population size.
  - Bayeux, St. Lo, Vire, Road Map Sheet No. 23 1944, 1:100,000; Crozier: "This map shows the three Omaha Beach critical military, first day objectives, i.e.: Town of Isigny, Trevieres, and Pointe de Hoc Fort at St. Pierre de Mont. All fell on June 6; St. Lo fell on July 18." (Item 20)
  - Vire, Domfront, Mayenne, Road Map Sheet No. 44 1944, 1:100,000 (Item 21)
  - Alencon, Argentan, La Ferte-Mace, Road Map Sheet No. 45 1944, 1:100,000 (Item 22)
  - Mamers, Laigle, Nogent, Le-Rotrou, Road Map Sheet No. 46 1944, 1:100,000 (Item 23)
  - Dreux, Verneuil, Nogent-Le-Rotrou, Road Map Sheet No. 47 1944, 1:100,000 (Item 24)
- Captured German Maps Depicting Caen and Surrounding Regions
  Two captured German maps.
  - Bildplan, Balleroy, Frankreich 1:25,000, XIV-12/3-4, Balleroy Nr. 3-4 1943, 1:25,000 (Item 25)
    Verm. u. Kart. Abt. 501.
    Reverse signed by Crozier
  - Deutsche Heerskarte, Caen, Frankreich 1:200,000, Nr. 14 1944, 1:200,000 (Item 26)
    Crozier; "Captured German map showing all our allied beachheads. Dated shortly before invasion.
    Colored map with legend in German.
- Celebratory Maps of First United States Army in Europe
  Two celebratory maps.
  - Operations of First United States Army in Europe, June 6, 1944 to May 9, 1945 1945 (Item 27)
    Maps depicts the drive from Normandy to Leipzeig, including the Normandy assault, St. Lo, Northern France pursuit, Siegfried Line, Ardennes Counteroffensive, Crossing of the Rhine, and Ruhr Pocket.
    Names of commanding officers on border.
    Divisional crests illustrated.
  - Special Map Showing Contact Between Gen. Hodges' First U.S. Army and Gen. Jadov's Fifth U.S.S.R. Army, 25 April 1945 (Item 28)
    Crozier: "U.S./Russian [contact] at the Elbe. Rare. Perhaps 300 printed."
    From map: Elements of 69th U.S. Division met elements of 58th U.S.S.R. Division at Torgau, Germany 25 April 1954 at 1640b.
    German Twelfth Army depicted.
- Various War Maps
  - Rhine River Bank Study G 1945, 1:12,500 (Item 29)
    North of Koeln
    Wall height along bank, river width and deep, jetty and harbors depicted.
  - Innsbruck and Environs 1944, 1:9,000 (Item 30)
    City street map
    Reverse list buildings and street index
  - Road and Bridge Data - First U.S. Army, Nideggen, Germany 1:25,000, Sheet 5304 1944, 1:25,000; Includes legend and index (Item 31)
  - Dresden, Germany 1:300,000, Sheet N52 1945, 1:300,000; Copied from a German road map dated 1938. (Item 32)
  - Cadzand 1, Holland 1:25,000, Sheet 451-1 1943, 1:25:000; Legend and glossary (Item 33)
  - Cadzand 2, Holland 1:25,000, Sheet 451-2 1943, 1:25:000; Legend and glossary (Item 34)
  - Koblenz, Germany 1:25,000, Sheet 5611 1944, 1:25,000; Legend, abbreviations, index (Item 35)
  - Theix, France 1:25,000, Sheet No. 22/30 S.W. 1944, 1:25,000 (Item 36)